616,572 years' worth of short-form
content is absorbed every single day
through one of these. 600,000 years.
Now, we are going through life, you
and me, I know,
and we have a little scrowl
every single day. Brain rot,
maybe some drunk Russian slipping on ice,
maybe cats
using up one of their nine lives.
I don't know.
And we have this guilt
that we carry around going,
we know this isn't good for us.
We know that these platforms work
meticulously to make this addictive,
whether it's
the swiping up that makes us feel like we
can't leave, like we're in a casino.
And actually, the casino thing
is very important here because human
beings love
gambling.
They love the potential upside of
something.
They love the fact
that maybe they could put a dollar down
and win a million.
Think about how many people do the
lottery. I know my mom and dad still do.
We love to play games where
if we just show up enough,
luck might come along and
change our circumstances.
But that's where gambling
and social media change.
Social media allows you to play a bet
every single day if you want to.
In fact,
every platform doesn't penalize you,
it rewards you for posting more.
So you get unlimited spins at the wheel
every day, as much as you want.
But at the casino, whether roulette,
blackjack, whatever it is,
as time goes on,
your odds only ever stay the same.
They're fixed.
When playing on a roulette table,
whether you play for a year, 10 years,
there's
still the amount of places on the rotating
wheel where the ball can land by chance.
In social media, this is different.
You are rewarded.
The longer you play,
the luckier you become.
The luck only ever builds towards you over
time. Let's look at skill acquisition.
Take it out of context.
You play a game of darts today with your
friend at the pub.
I force you to play.
And let's imagine you play a game of
hitting one, then hitting
two, then hitting three, hitting four,
and you get one go each until you've hit
all
the numbers around the dart board.
There's going to be a certain amount of
throws of the dart it's going to take you
to do it. Now, every day after work,
I'm now going to force you to have two
pints
and to play a game of darts with your
mate.
In a year's time,
I get you to do the same game.
You're going to be much better.
Without coaching,
without having any lessons,
without studying a course, just
through doing it every day.
Because there's motor control changes
where you throw
one and it goes wildly off.
You think to yourself, "Cool,
best not do that again."
And then the opposite of that,
you throw one with a certain type of
technique or a
certain flick of the wrist and it hits,
and you go, "Wow, I'm going to start
doubling down on that." That's just simple
motor units in the brain learning the
path. The same way
that picking up my phone right now
and talking to it, or even
talking to that camera right there,
is going to do the exact same thing.
So you would get better at darts as time
goes on.
The other thing we need to consider here
is with someone gambling, every time they
bet, they lose something, often money,
and they're penalized to gamble with small
amounts because the upsides
are never going to be the same.
Social media is free to use. Free.
For unlimited spins.
And it is technically gambling. It
is my favorite type of gambling because
just
before I throw the dice
and I get to load them through preparing
what I'm going to
say, strategizing a hook,
even picking a good title.
Fellow in front of me,
the title of this video
is "The Ridiculous Evolution of
Short-Form Content." That's me loading my
die. I think die is plural for dice.
I don't know.
And every time I continue my gambling
addiction with social media
like this, the odds
are forever building in my favor, and
that excites me.
And the beautiful part is,
if I lose today, if this video bombs,
I lose
nothing but the time and the breath
that came out of my mouth recording this
video.
This is the most beautiful casino
and the most positive gambling you could
ever have in your life because content
creation is a skill
that you can carry into
anything you do. Even
if your online venture
or thing you're doing doesn't work
out,
the skills that you learn from editing
jump cuts, you could put a visual
CV together to send to your next employer.
You could make up a creative video to send
to a girl that you want to take on a
date. Now, in the casino,
pattern recognition,
unless you can count cards in
blackjack, won't save you.
So for instance, in roulette,
it doesn't matter how well
you know the numbers on the wheel or
which one's next to which,
you can't exactly
time or get the croupier to get it in a
certain. Pattern recognition is dead.
Even some of you may
or may not have noticed
that you get a load of numbers that
come up on the roulette table telling you
what's come up.
It's called the gambler's fallacy,
and in essence, what's happening
is the house is
trying to put into your mind, okay,
there's been seven black numbers in a row.
You create a narrative in your head, oh,
the next one's got to be a red, which is
false, by the way.
The odds remain the same irrelevant of
that.
Giving people that information
is probably make them more likely to make
a mistake
than not. However,
the pattern recognition
that you can get from gambling on social
media is vastly different.
You make 20 videos,
each one based off a problem that
your client faces,
whether it's reducing their corp tax,
helping them lose weight,
whatever. Of those 20 videos,
you look at which one did well and
which one didn't.
Now we need to decipher with pattern
recognition, was it topic?
Was it the way in which the video
was made? Was it point and shoot?
Was it perfectly curated?
Was I reading a teleprompter?
Was I doing it on a dog walk?
Those pattern recognitions we can then
fuel to create
the next videos. Even this video today
is based off pattern recognition
that I saw
from another outlier channel.
I saw a creator get over 300,000 views on
a certain
type of video, and I thought,
I could make a certain type of video just
like that
for my audience. Now, once I take
that pattern recognition of the things in
front
of me that I see well,
that thing's doing well, take
that to my motor unit
recruitment of me becoming better at the
thing that I'm doing because I do it every
day.
We now have the perfect storm for
virality, for getting thousands,
hundreds of thousands,
potentially millions of people to see the
thing I'm talking
about. Now, the best part
is even the best employee will only work
9:00 to
5:00. They'll want weekends off.
They'll want two weeks holiday a year.
They're going to want wages,
maybe their pension, whatever it is.
Social media works 24 hours a day,
seven days a week, nonstop.
The algorithms are changed on a day-by-day
basis, and they create every single
platform to be the most addictive possible
to keep the people on there the most
amount of time so they can spread your
videos to people that need them or want
them. These platforms
are working tirelessly to break down the
barriers of making
content creation easier.
Instagram created edits.
TikTok created CapCut.
Before that, you had to use VideoLeap,
and there was complexities to different
platforms. And back in my day,
which makes me sound old, 2018, we had to
type out our captions frame by frame.
There was no auto captions.
That's how long I've been creating
content.
Short-form content drives all my
businesses apart from this mentorship.
New Tonic does over a million dollars a
month, short-form content.
Three Sunday Times
and one best-selling books,
all short-form content.
My personal training app,
the James Smith Academy,
140,000 people through the
doors, all short-form content.
There's 100,000 people
that follow the Instagram
page for it. Right now,
you might think that potentially,
I don't know, I'm
pretty good at presenting to camera.
There's two things you're looking at right
now.
Topic of this video,
pattern recognition and motor unit skills.
Been doing this a long time.
The thing that makes me confident
is probably the
undeniable proof
that I've built up over the years making
short-form content.
My one lesson to you from this
is everything that you hear that's
negative about
short-form content can't be negative for
your business at the same time.
There's a paradox here. If it's
that bad as a consumer,
it's equally great as a
creator. Think about that for a second.
The more addictive
and time-consuming it
is becoming for a consumer,
the more you are going to get views,
engagement,
and build your personal brand as a
creator.
There's so much negativity about the ways
these algorithms and platforms
are moving,
which should be showing you where the
opportunity is as a personal
brand and a creator to make content.
Every day, thousands of people
are getting into content.
The landscape of getting seen
is getting harder by the minute.
Today has to be the day
that you take the first move in starting
to create
short-form content.
My Short-Form Content Mastery course
is going to be linked in
the description. It's 99 US dollars.
It's like 70 quid.
Teaches you everything you need to know
about creating your first 100 pieces of
content. Once you've done those,
you'll be on a roll.
Imagine if I said for 99 US dollars,
I could personally ensure that you
trained every single day for 100 days.
It would be pretty easy for you to
maintain that momentum afterwards.
Everywhere I go around the world,
I always bump into people in airports, and
actually once in a nightclub, "Hey, mate,
I've done your Short-Form Content Mastery
course." I want you to become one of those
people.
Do I think it's going to add millions of
dollars of rev to your business? No.
What I do think is it's going to turn you
from someone that occasionally uses
social media to someone
that truly sees the benefits
and reaps the benefits of it.
Everything amazing
that I have in my life
is from creating short-form content.
I would like you to experience the same.
So check the link out in the description,
and if you're still not interested, watch
this video here because YouTube recommends
that you'll like it.